So, welcome back to the TRT and hormone
optimization YouTube channel. And we
have back with us as a guest, Dr.
Jeffrey Rutderbush. Welcome back,
Jeffrey.
>> Well, thanks so much for having me back,
Stephen.
>> You're very welcome. So, let's talk
today about daily micro doing
testosterone for TRT. So, uh you wrote
me that you have some new experiences
with it that you wanted to share.
Well, yes, that you know throughout my
practice it's evolved. It's always
evolving. And when you think about it,
you know, God doesn't have our testicles
secrete testosterone once a week, twice
a week, thrice a week. It's a daily, you
dial pattern.
And so I got thinking about that. I
said, "Well, let's try to mimic
our daily physiological dosing as best
as we can."
So, and I heard about it. Uh, some
friends of mine were doing it.
So,
every morning now I have not only
myself, but I have my patients now um
either do it's a very small amount
obviously doing daily doses. Currently
my regimen now is 20 milligrams which is
0.1 ml
uh every morning. So that's 140
milligrams per week. Now that may not
seem like a lot but even when I'm on 20
milligrams a week.
Now, my trough given that protocol would
be have my bloods drawn the morning
uh before I did that 20 milligrams. Now,
I've done that several times over the
past year and even at 140 milligrams per
week, 20 milligrams per day, my
testosterone is still greater than 1500.
In fact, I even tried
after I injected 20 milligrams one day,
I waited three days
where I got my labs drawn. I figured I'd
tough out big time. I was still greater
than 1500.
>> Three days out after only 20 milligrams.
So given that, I had I'm recommending
all my patients
to micro dose. And I may sound like a
nuisance, but tell you something. 0.1 ml
as you know Stephen is very very small
bit it's just a little bit so what I do
is after I inject and given that volume
you can do that IM or subq it's painless
but what I do is every time I inject
myself the very first thing I do is put
my needle back into my testosterone
and rather than hold it because it takes
a while it's it's syrupy being a very
thin needle, but I don't hold it. I just
go ahead and put it in.
I have this old hydrogen peroxide bottle
that has a great amount. I can put the
needle and and testo also right in it.
Put it next to my sink while I'm
brushing my teeth or washing my face or
whatever. And actually two minutes, it's
already filled up. So I just take it
out, set it for the 0.1 ml, cap it off
so it's ready for the next day. My point
is, yes, you have to do it more often,
but given such a small volume, it
doesn't take very long get.1
ml drawn up. That's how we do it now. 20
milligrams a day. I've even had some
people
use
10 milligrams per day and they're still
greater than 1,200
two days out. Remember our body only
naturally produces four to seven
milligrams per day. So if you take that
range four to seven now the low end of
that be four time seven 28 milligrams
for testosterone per week. The high end
would be 49.
>> Somewhere between 28 and 49 milligrams
per week is what our body produces
naturally. So given that 20 milligrams a
day is still greater than that. But you
get you have that little bit of weight
there from the from the esther. But I
just feel that micro doing
as close to mimicking our own god-given
pulses is the best way to go. And given
that also I don't have you know
everybody's worried about their
estrogen.
We have still have to deal with that. I
don't really measure anymore. But some
of my patient come in and worry about
their estrogen. I have found that micro
doing it doesn't really elevate estrogen
enough to where people even are
concerned about it. So I don't have to
allay their fears about their estrogen
causing them symptoms.
So [clears throat] I have to worry about
that. I know that, but I don't have to
worry about so much about SHBG anymore
because if I'm mimicking our normal
daily pulses, whether a guy's got a low
SHBG or a higher SHBG,
I don't have to worry about it. I'm just
doing daily doses. So, I just I mimic
what God has done for us naturally. And
given that, I I feel like I'm doing the
patient justice. I have I have to worry
about supra physsiological doses causing
anything unusual. And since I started
that over a year ago for all my
patients,
the patients
like it. I've had very few complaints
about it. Every feels more dialed in.
Um, and so not only are my total
testosterones where I like them to be,
but my free testosterones are where I
think it should be. Somewhere between 20
and 30 nanograms per deciliter, but I
feel most of my men feel better if I get
their pre-tes be 20 above 25 and
sometimes 35 or 40
>> and they're all dialed in at that. So
micro doing even though it's a little
more cumbersome, it's really not once
you get used to it. Um takes less time
to do that than brushing your teeth. So
I recommend everybody. So all my
patients now are micro doing and they're
much much happier with it.
>> Mhm. But since you're dosing daily, does
the esther still matter? Can you use
propionate or do you still use cipionate
or any cipinate you can use
uh propriate and antante. So given the
esester and the weight of the esters I
just find that I can use any some people
even use the sustenon which has three
esters I believe and they do you know 20
milligrams of that and they feel
wonderful. I've had so few complaints
other than, "Oh, doc, I got to do it
every day." But once they get used to
it, it's so nominal. It's so effortless
and it's painfree.
>> And all your patients are agreeing to do
that daily. Do they also come from twice
a week, three times a week?
>> They're all in agreement. But if I can
if I you know I talk to them about the
basic physiology involved with it and
how it's replicating God's normal
pulses. Um many I haven't gotten them
all to convert to it yet because some
are happy on their twice a week dosing
or um but I've gotten probably 80% of my
patients now over time on the daily 20
milligrams or less a micro
>> dose.
But how can that be mimicking the normal
daily rhythm um with these esters? They
stay in your blood for a longer time.
No.
>> Yeah. Well, they do. And and that's why
I'm still working on it. Um that's why
when I I did my blood most recently and
I checked my my blood levels three days
out after 20 milligrams, it was still
greater than,500.
>> Yeah.
>> But a bottom line, remember, I'm
treating people. So I I say how you
feel? I feel great. So I don't care what
their numbers are. Um I find the
secondary ruthytosis
is much more easily managed on these
smaller doses.
>> And that's another thing too. You know
people don't hate don't eat blood. You
know we don't we know you don't have to
but it's good for you in the community
to do so. I I still donate blood about
every four months. Are hematocrits lower
doing daily dozing?
>> Yes. Yes. Now I still have a you know
some people still respond some people
convert uh some people get a secondary
rifytosis no matter what dose you use
but I still find out that on these
smaller micro doing daily micro dosing
the amount of secondary ariththroytosis
is greatly minimized. We heard the
drawbacks. We heard the many benefits
maybe. Um and also yeah, I think uh you
just must convince the man to start
doing it daily and once they experience
it, they're going along with it.
>> Every patient that I've talked into
converting from once a week, twice a
week, thrice a week, a daily,
they've all
told me that I've gotten great feedback.
I've never gotten such more positive
feedback from a certain remember I've
been doing this for over 40 years. So
I've had a lot of feedback on all these
protocols, but I've never had in general
a greater positive feedback rate on a
dosing technique
with both clients
and outcome than this one.
>> Yeah. Awesome. Thanks for sharing.
Hey,
hey, hey.